{"tossups": [{"question": "This man painted himself into the skin of Saint Bartholomew in The Last Judgment, an entry in a series of frescoes this man painted in a Vatican chapel. This man's sculpted (*) Pieta, a statue of Mary cradling the body of Jesus, and created a statue of a slingshot-holding marble David. For ten points, name this Italian who painted the Sistine Chapel ceiling.", "answer": "Michelangelo di Lodovico Buonarroti Simoni", "subcategory": "Fine Arts Visual", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "On the day before this holiday, some believers practice kapparot, the swinging of a chicken. This holiday includes readings from the Book of Jonah and ends with the ne'ila prayer. The Kol Nidre prayer is recited on this last of the High Holy Days that follow (*) Rosh Hashanah. This holiday includes a day of fasting and vidui, the confession of sins. For ten points, name this Jewish\" Day of Atonement.\"", "answer": "Yom Kippur (accept Day of Atonement before it is read)", "subcategory": "Religion Judaism", "category": "Religion"}, {"question": "This event was covered by Herbert Morrison, a Chicago reporter whose voice was accidentally sped up as he described the \"falling on the mooring-mast\" during this event. The LZ 129's arrival at the Lakehurst Naval (*) Air Station preceded the cry \"Oh, the humanity!\" during this disaster. For ten points, name this 1937 tragedy in New Jersey, in which thirty-five people died aboard a German zeppelin that caught fire.", "answer": "LZ 129 Hindenburg disaster", "subcategory": "History American", "category": "History"}, {"question": "In this type of motion, reference frames experience the fictitious Coriolis force. Precession is a change in the orientation of objects experiencing this type of motion. Forces that take effect when objects are moving in this way include (*) torque and centrifugal force, which is experienced by gyroscopes. For ten points, name this type of movement in which an object spins around an axis.", "answer": "rotation (accept word forms like rotating; prompt on descriptions like \"spinning\" or \"turning\" before \"spins\" is read)", "subcategory": "Science Physics", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "This player caused Mike Breen to add a second \"bang\" to his catchphrase by hitting a near half-court shot to defeat Oklahoma City. This player struck a fan with his (*) mouthguard during a 14-point loss in Game 6 of the 2016 NBA Finals. The Splash Brothers are Klay Thompson and, for ten points, what Under Armour spokesman and long-range point guard, the currently reigning NBA MVP for the Golden State Warriors?", "answer": "Stephen \"Steph\" Curry", "category": "Trash"}, {"question": "This author wrote about Brigid, who \"wrecks her life\" by washing herself invisible and then uses \"super-indelible\" markers to fix the problem in Purple Green and Yellow. This author of (*) Thomas' Snowsuit wrote books in which Princess Elizabeth befriends a dragon and a mother pledges \"as long as I'm living / my baby you'll be.\" For ten points, name this Canadian children's author of The Paper Bag Princess and Love You Forever.", "answer": "Robert Norman Munsch", "category": "Trash"}, {"question": "This god was accompanied into battle by Geri and Freki, since he gave them all his food. This god will attack Fenrir with his spear, Gungnir, at Ragnarok, and he kept Huginn and Muninn, a pair of messenger (*) ravens. This god gained wisdom from the Well of Mimir by losing an eye. For ten points, identify this chief Norse god, the father of Thor.", "answer": "Odin (accept Wotann)", "subcategory": "Mythology Norse", "category": "Mythology"}, {"question": "The size of these natural phenomena is determined by the \"fetch\" behind them. When these things \"break,\" they release kinetic energy as matter falls from its maximum amplitude. These phenomena may \"shoal\" in (*) shallow water, and they do not occur when there is no wind. For ten points, name this physical phenomenon, a rippling motion on the surface of a body of water.", "answer": "surface waves (accept ocean waves; accept descriptions like waves on the surface of water)", "subcategory": "Science Other", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "In a novel by this author, Edward Ferrars and Colonel Brandon marry Elinor and Marianne Dashwood, who represent the title concepts. In another work by this author, Mr Darcy falls in love with (*) Elizabeth Bennett despite their preconceived ideas about each other. For ten points, name this English author of \"sentimental novels\" like Emma, Sense and Sensibility, and Pride and Prejudice.", "answer": "Jane Austen", "subcategory": "Literature British", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "To celebrate the opening of the Panama Canal, this city held a 1915 exposition in its Balboa Park. This city's namesake bay, which opens between Point Loma and (*) Coronado, is home to the United States Navy's Pacific fleet. Mission Bay is home to Sea World in this city, where Balboa Park houses a large open-air zoo. For ten points, name this city in southern California directly across the border from Tijuana.", "answer": "San Diego, California", "subcategory": "Geography American", "category": "Geography"}, {"question": "This country owned a colony that expanded as far south as Fort Ross in modern-day Sonoma. In 1848, St. Michael's Cathedral was built in this country's colonial town of (*) Sitka. In 1867, this country received $7.2 million in a land deal orchestrated by Secretary of State William Seward, labeled a \"folly\" by his opponents. For ten points, name this country whose American colonies, including Alaska, were founded in the name of the tsars.", "answer": "Russian Empire (do not accept \"USSR\" or \"Soviet Russia\")", "subcategory": "History American", "category": "History"}, {"question": "This country's first prime minister, Count Cavour, made a secret alliance with Napoleon. This modern country unified under King Victor Emmanuel II in the Risorgimento. The Redshirts under (*) Giuseppe Garibaldi fought for, for ten points, what European country that includes land held by the former kingdoms of Sardinia, Naples, Sicily, and Rome?", "answer": "Italy (accept Italia)", "subcategory": "History European", "category": "History"}, {"question": "An ion of this element forms the hydrophilic \"heads\" of the molecules in the cell membrane's bilayer. One allotrope of this element will, on exposure to oxygen, faintly glow in the dark. Three atoms of this element are present in the end product of (*) cellular respiration, ATP. For ten points, name this Group 15 chemical element, found just below nitrogen on the periodic table, with symbol P.", "answer": "phosphorus (accept P before it is read)", "subcategory": "Science Chemistry", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "n this play, Thomas Danforth reveals that a doll made by Mary Warren has been found in the protagonist's home, skewered on a pin. In this play, Elizabeth's husband, John, has an affair with (*) Abigail Williams. Giles Corey demands \"more weight\" until he is crushed to death, and the slave Tituba is accused of casting curses in, for ten points, what play by Arthur Miller about the Salem witch trials?", "answer": "The Crucible", "subcategory": "Literature American", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "After this event, critics complained that no \"official notice\" was given that Article 50 would be invoked. In this event's aftermath, Theresa May replaced David Cameron as (*) Prime Minister. Stock markets plunged after news broke of, for ten points, what June 2016 public referendum that decided to end a namesake country's participation in the European Union?", "answer": "Brexit (accept descriptions of the United Kingdom's June 2016 referendum to leave the European Union; accept equivalents, like Britain's vote to leave the EU; prompt on partial answers)", "subcategory": "Current Events Other", "category": "Current Events"}, {"question": "This composer played his 26th piano concerto at the coronation of Leopold II, even though he had not written out much of the left hand part. This composer's 13th serenade for string quartet, listed as number 525 in the (*) Ko \u0308chel catalogue, is nicknamed \"Eine Kleine Nachtmusik\"or \"A Little Night Music.\" For ten points, name this Austrian composer, a child prodigy who wrote Don Giovanni.", "answer": "Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart", "subcategory": "Fine Arts Auditory", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "After a 1982 assassination attempt in Dujail, this man ordered the executions of over 140 Shiites believed to be involved. This leader, who was found in 2003 near Tikrit in a (*) \"spider hole,\" was hanged for crimes against humanity in 2006. This dictator's 1991 invasion of Kuwait sparked the first Gulf War, and he was deposed by US forces in the second Gulf War. For ten points, name this former leader of Iraq.", "answer": "Saddam Hussein (prompt on \"Saddam\" alone)", "subcategory": "History World", "category": "History"}, {"question": "These systems cannot be formed from immiscible fluids. In chemistry, these substances can become supersaturated under certain conditions, then shocked to make a precipitate. Water is considered a (*) \"universal\" part of these substances, since it can combine evenly with many other chemicals. For ten points, give this term for a homogeneous mixture of a solute in a solvent.", "answer": "solutions", "subcategory": "Science Chemistry", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "In the Arabian Nights, Sinbad collects diamonds from an island inhabited by enormous ones of these animals called rocs [\"rocks\"], and later steals one of their (*) eggs. Chanticleer is one of these creatures in French folklore, and a mythical animal of this type is a phoenix. For ten points, name this family of animals, exemplified by Chicken Little.", "answer": "birds (accept aves or avians)", "subcategory": "Literature Other", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "A square with the same area as one of these shapes can't be drawn with compass and straightedge alone. You cannot draw one of these shapes through a non-square rhombus's four vertices; as a result, those rhombuses are not (*) cyclic. An ellipse with both focuses at the same point is essentially, for ten points, what shape, defined as all points an equal distance away from a center, through which a diameter can be drawn?", "answer": "circle", "subcategory": "Science Math", "category": "Science"}], "bonuses": []}